

#### **PROFILE**

A Development professional with 5 years of experience in grassroots to raise awareness, educate/train/facilitate, & serve to empower stakeholders. I am passionate about capacitating individuals to achieve their full potential and catalyzing in helping their lives transform to the best of my capacities through different interventions. I seek an opportunity in the sector to utilize my skills and interests in the larger good. My objective is mutual gain and growth by contributing empathetically and ethically to the human development space.

### CONTACT

Phone- 9403384667

LinkedIn- https://www.linkedin.com/in/pra

tiksha-kalpraj-369985166/

Email ID-

pratiksha.abroad2024@gmail.com

## PERSONAL DETAILS

Name- Pratiksha Kalpraj

Birth date- 18 Feb. 1995

Location- Pune (Native-Jalgaon, Maha,)

HOBBIES

Singing

Acting

Networking

Travelling

# LANGUAGES

Marathi

English

Hindi

Ahirani

# Pratiksha Kalpraj

Development Practitioner | Trainer-Facilitator | Consultant

WORK EXPERIENCE

(Total experience - 5 years)

Independent consultant

Sept. 2023- July 2024

Worked on an independent assignment for a CSR organization focusing on Gender Sensitization and Community Leadership Development with Adolescent Boys in the Nashik district. Tasks included curriculum structuring, content creation, project intervention facilitation, report writing, and documentation.

Training & Capacity Building Master Trainer- Life Skills, empowHER India, Karjat.

Aug 2022- Sep 2023

- Empowered 500+ adolescent girls to achieve Behavior change through Life skills education in the remotes of dist. Raigad
- Catalyzed the programmatic processes by working closely with operations teams in Data collection, Community and resource mobilization, and Program design.
- 3. Built and handled field cluster teams with a quality focus. Trained them to disseminate the modules on Life skills, Health and Nutrition, Gender & Financial literacy. Monitored training activities in the field, ensuring effective program execution.
- 4. Planned & Conducted training of trainers (TOTs) & Refresher training for different stakeholders in the community.
- Developed content for training and delivered the same. Gender neutralized the content for the Co-ed programs in ZP schools.
- 6. Identified effective and creative non-content activities (Icebreakers/Energizers) and incorporated them into the curriculum.
- Intervened with a group of Adolescent girls in a village envisaging a sustainable change in their behavior & attitudes.
- Generated weekly/monthly reports on Training evaluation, emphasizing quantitative/qualitative analysis of the team's performance.

## Independent Contractor

(Jan 21-Jul 22)

Assisted individual clients, non-profit and government organizations in training, facilitation, proposal writing, personal advisory, and documentation. Helped a grassroots organization with human capacity building and development through candidate selection, networking, and outreach.

District Lead, Swastha Bharat Prerak, Tata Trusts | Nashik

(Jul 2019-Sep 2020)

- Provided managerial support to National Nutrition Mission i.e., POSHAN Abhiyaan (ICDS) Women & Child Development.
- 2. Capacitated a team of 5000+ Anganwadi workers to improve their core service delivery effectively. Sensitized & empowered them to cater to the Pregnant & Lactating mothers about Healthy pre-natal practices & importance of Proper nutrition. Conducted a Sector-level intervention for Social-behavioral Change Communications covering 100+ women
- 3. Led a Team of 25+ Block Co-coordinators to catalyze Data filling & Technical support at the block level. Improved Inter-Department Convergence & Liaising for Effective implementation of the program.
- 4. Monitored ICDS-CAS rollout & handled Real-time data of district.
- Appreciated by the CEO, ZP for contributing to the district in achieving Ist Rank in the state in 'POSHAN Maah' for the subsequent 2 yrs.

### **COMPETANCIES**

#### Thematic work-

- Training & capacity Building
- Life skills & Gender Education
- Skill and Content development
- Working with Youth & Adolescents
- Menstrual health & hygiene
- Women & Child Nutrition

### Domain Skills

- Community Mobilization
- Report & Proposal Writing
- Project Management
- Need assessment & Micro Planning
- Government Liaising

## Personal strengths -

- Leadership & Pro-activeness,
- Public Speaking & team building
- Adaptability & Field competency
- Development communications
- Professional values & work ethics

## IT skills-

• Microsoft Office, Canva

## Research -

- Secondary education of SC & ST Adolescent girls- Case study of Jalgaon district in Maharashtra. (MA Research)
- Understanding the menstrual hygiene practices, social taboo around menstruation & needs of thewomen in Nashik. (Pilot study)

## Certifications-

- Experiential Learning Tools & Mentoring Skills by YASHADA, Pune (DoPT, GOI)
- Women Entre. Development Program, Symbiosis Pune.
- Soft skills trainer- National Institute of Skills Training

# Other Endeavors-

- Amateur theatrist and singer
- India's largest Entrepreneurship Odyssey (Jagriti Yatra 2021 & 2022)

Professional references available if needed.

### **FIELDWORK**

Intern at Integrated Tribal Development Project Ghodegaon, Pune

- Led projects on Agro-tourism campsites development and Sustainable Menstruation as Alternate Livelihoods for Tribal stakeholders
- Facilitated 150 beneficiaries developing the Agro tourism campsites through Entrepreneurship Development training (EDP).
- Guided over 1000 Adolescent girls on Sustainable Menstruation Practices & MHH from Ashram schools.
- Appreciated for the Field intervention by the Program Officer, ITDP.

### Intern at 'Disasters & Beyond Project' Osmanabad, by TISS Mumbai. 2 M

- Worked closely with MSRLM's UMED Abhiyaan to collectivize women to impart skill training.
- Stakeholder identification and analysis of risks & vulnerabilities faced by these communities to their livelihoods in 3 villages.
- Conducted a situational analysis with Livelihood mapping & Intergenerational Asset mapping tools.
- Capacitated 500+ SHG Women to explore Alternate Livelihood opportunities in Draught prone areas through Entrepreneurship Development Programs.
- Educated them on government schemes & helped 40+ families benefit and facilitated them to start up their Ventures.

## Intern at CORO India, Mumbai (Concurrent Field work)

I Yr

I M

- Collectivized 50+ women from lower-income groups in Slums in SHGs.
- Contributed to starting up their Enterprises & Collective activities leveraging BMC schemes.
- Encouraged them to develop Entrepreneurial skills through VEDPs.

## **EDUCATION**

$\triangleright$	MA Social Work (Livelihood & Social Ent.)	-	TISS, Mumbai	2017-19
>	PG Dip. (Gender, Culture & Dev. Studies)	1	SPPU, Pune	2016-17
	Bachelor of Arts in Sociology		KBC NMU, Jalgaon	2014-16

## **DECLARATION**

Hereby I confirm that, to the best of my knowledge, the provided information is true & accurate by this submission.

Yours,

Pratiksha Kalpraj